<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consideration of certaine positions archiepiscopall</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115506</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850725</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 950:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consideration of certaine positions archiepiscopall</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618. Proposition. Concerning kneeling in the very act of receiving howsoever. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12; 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[W. Jones's secret press?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604-05]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Printer and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>"A proposition. Concerning kneeling in the very act of receiuing howsoever" (29 p. at end) has separate title page dated 1605.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Posture in worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15950:1"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A CONSIDERATION <hi>OF CERTAINE POSITIONS</hi> Archiepiſcopall.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="position">
                     <head>1 Religion cannot ſtand without ſome Ceremonies, as kneeling &amp;c.</head>
                     <p>REligion is the feare of God to ſerue him preciſely according to his word, and therefore it is called <hi>Godlines. Iſa: 29.13. Act: 2.5. &amp; 10; 2. &amp; 26.5. 2: Tim: 3.5. Heb: 9.1. Iam. 1.27.</hi> As by Superſtition his Majeſtie mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth, when one reſtreignes himſelfe to any other rule in the ſervice of God, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is warranted by the word. <hi>Bas. dor. pag 15.</hi> Which is therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>Wilworſhip. Col: 2.21.23.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Howſoever it be <hi>Religion,</hi> out of the feare and loue of God, to keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts as well of the ſecond as firſt table, yet the conſcionable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of the commandements con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d in the firſt table is, by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, called <hi>Religion;</hi> And wheras
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15950:2"/> man cannot judge of ſuch obſerving the firſt and third commandements therfore is he eſteemed <hi>Religious,</hi> who maketh conſcience of the 2 and 4: commandements; In ſanctifiyng the Sabbath with ſuch an outward man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhip, as is not after mans invention, but according to Gods word.</p>
                     <p>So that by <hi>Religion,</hi> in this poſition is meant the outward (eſpecially publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que) worſhip of God: <hi>Religion</hi> being put for <hi>worſhip,</hi> becauſe the feare of God to ſerue him preciſely accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to his word, is, of all the actions of men, eſpecially to be manifeſted in worſhipping God. Who will be ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in all them that come nere him if they offer ſtrange fire. <hi>Levit: 10.3. Religion</hi> (then) being put for <hi>Outward worſhip,</hi> the poſition is granted. For in deed the outward worſhip of God doth conſiſt only of ceremonies, that is, outward demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of inward
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15950:2"/> worſhip. But, how doth this follow, The outward worſhip of God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſtand without ſome Ceremonies, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go. It cannot ſtand without the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in queſtion? As though <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> had no better ground than <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Biſhops</hi> haue, according to this maxime: <hi>No Ceremony, no Biſhop.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But more clearely to perceiue the truth, it is to be conſidered that ſome ceremonies by nature, or generall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome demonſtrate inward worſhipp is not only ſignes thereof, but effects alſo. Other doe the ſame, as ſignes on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By which inſtituted ceremonies God is not worſhipped except they be by himſelfe preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; For as no fire could make any ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice a ſavor of reſt to God, but that which came from God. <hi>Levit. 9.24.</hi> and <hi>10.1.2:</hi> So no warrant can make outward worſhip, or any part thereof acceptable to God, but that which commeth from God. <hi>Math. 15.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15950:3"/>
                     <p>Therfore it doth not follow, that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>kneeling</hi> in prayer is lawful, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the ceremonies in queſtion (na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Surplice</hi>) be ſo to. For 1: Nature teacheth us to manifeſt inward reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence by outward geſtures. 2 Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cuſtome amongſt us maketh <hi>knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> the moſt ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſigne of the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt reverence. <hi>3</hi> In true worſhippers of God <hi>kneeling</hi> is not only a ſigne of inward worſhip, but an effect alſo. 4: It is warranted by the word. And 5 it is not appropriated to the outward worſhip of God: For men doe uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; may lawfully, demonſtrat their inward reverencing of men by knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Wheras the ceremonies in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (namely the ſurplice) do not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monſtrat inward worſhip by nature: For then all religious worſhippers would (at leaſt) haue a diſpoſition to uſe the ſurplice at all times, and in all places. (2) None can affirme, that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall cuſtome maketh a Surplice a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15950:3"/> ſigne of inward worſhip. Becauſe the publicke uſe of it is moſt what omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or inforced, and there is no ſuch matter as the private uſe thereof, and by privat perſons. In both which con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiderations it may be <hi>(3)</hi> denyed to be an effecte of inward worſhip, and the rather if it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be proved to be an effecte of the obedience of faith to ſome commandement of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the ſame. Which (4) cannot be; Seyng in all the new Teſtament there is nether precept, nor example; nor other matter of neceſſary conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion warranting the ſame. And yet (5 It is appropriated to the ſervice of God, and therfore ſuperſtitious, and not religious, eſpecially beyng urged as it is.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="position">
                     <head>
                        <hi>2</hi> Ceremonies are lawfull, when their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is lawfull.</head>
                     <p>If by Doctrin of ceremonies be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their <hi>ſignification,</hi> then the <hi>Th ſis</hi> is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyed: For then other Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſh ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15950:4"/> may be reſtored. As <hi>ſetting up of Candles</hi> to ſignifie that the workes of all chriſtians, <hi>Phil. 2.15.</hi> eſpecially Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. <hi>Math: 5.14.16.</hi> ſhould ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men; and yet it is pronounced in the 3 Injunction to be <hi>deviſed by mans phantaſie, beſides ſcripture,</hi> and therfore <hi>Superſtitious.</hi> And <hi>vnleavened bread</hi> in the Lords ſupper may ſignify <hi>Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> &amp; <hi>truth. 1: Cor: 5.8.</hi> And yet by the Communion booke (<hi>Rub:</hi> after the Communion ſect: 5.) it is reformed, <hi>To take away the ſuperſtition, which any perſon hath, or might haue:</hi> But many haue, and may haue Superſtition in Ceremonies reteined.</p>
                     <p>If the meaning of the poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be this <hi>Ceremonyes are lawfull, when they are warranted by lawfull doctrine,</hi> it is to be graunted; but then the <hi>Hypotheſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> muſt be denyed. For it is <hi>petitio prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii</hi> to affirme; that Ceremonies in queſtion are ſo warranted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="position">
                     <head>
                        <hi>3</hi> The doctrine of Ceremonies is part of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15950:4"/> the Goſpell.</head>
                     <p>This poſition is true, but onely accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f ceremonies by inſtitution. Which doctrine is either <hi>affirmatiue,</hi> ſhewing what Ceremonyes by inſtitution are to be uſed, and thoſe be only the two Sacraments, which are indeed <hi>Seal s,</hi> and not onely Ceremonyes. Or <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue,</hi> teaching what ceremonies are not to be vſed. viz: Neither Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> nor traditions of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.<hi>20.21.23.</hi> Neither <hi>Carnall rites. Gal.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Heb. 9.10.</hi> Nor comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of men. <hi>Col. 2.22.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which negatiue doctrine of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes, is indeed according to the truth of the Goſpell. <hi>Gal. 2.3.5.12.14</hi> and that is contrary to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Becauſe that law ſtood in carnall rites. Heb. 9.10.11. That is, Ceremonies inſtituted to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct &amp; direct the outward man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inward ſervice of God, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15950:5"/> was that law called <hi>a carnal com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement.</hi> Heb: 7.16. and thoſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes accounted <hi>Rudiments of the world.</hi> Gal 4.3. So that after faith (that is the Goſpel) came, that law, and the Ceremonies therof gaue place, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſſe perfect, a childiſh paedagogy &amp; beggerly rudiments. 1 Cor: 13.10.11. Gal. 3 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 4.2.3.9. In reſpect of the more perfect word of Chriſt, <hi>Col: 3.</hi>16. 2 Cor: 3.13.17.18. Who is that <hi>Meſsias,</hi> who, when he cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, did tell us althinges concerning the outward worſhip of God. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.<hi>19.20.25.26.</hi> But Chriſt never told us the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes in queſtion.</p>
                     <p>Therefore if the negatiue doctrine againſt <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Ceremonyes inſtituted by God to the purpoſes aforeſaid, be part of the Goſpell, or <hi>word of Chriſt,</hi> much more is the negatiue doctrine againſt ceremonyes inſtituted by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſame purpoſes, without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the <hi>word,</hi> part of the Goſpell.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15950:5"/> 
                        <hi>Col. 2.20.22.23. Gal: 1.6.7.8.10.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e rather; becauſe the word ſayth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>at they, who burthen the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith ordinances of the world, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e traditions after the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ents and doctrines of men, doe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>old <hi>Chriſt</hi> the head. Col. 2.19.20.22 &amp; 3.1. and oppoſing ſuch traditions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o the commandements of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ith of Ieſus, maketh them parte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e beaſtes marke. <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.9 12. Here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto accordeth that which is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the booke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer, in the preface of Ceremonyes, viz. <hi>Chriſt his Goſpell is not a Ceremoniall law (as much of</hi> Moſes <hi>was) but it is a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> to ſerue God, not in bondage of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure or ſhadow, but in the freedome of ſpirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="position">
                     <head>
                        <hi>4</hi> Miniſters refuſing Conformitie are Schiſmatiques.</head>
                     <p>This word <hi>Schiſme</hi> according to thnow receaved uſe thereof in the Church, ſignifieth <hi>A voluntary ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15950:6"/> of the Church onely for matters of the outward goverment thereof. So that Schiſmatiques</hi> are by Doctor <hi>Bancroft,</hi> in his Notes before his Sermon at <hi>Pauls</hi> croſſe, Anno 1588. defined as out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> to be ſuch, <hi>as retei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with us the true faith, ſeperat them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues from us for orders and Ceremonies.</hi> In which ſence though <hi>Brow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſt:</hi> (ſo called) may be deemed <hi>Schiſmatickes,</hi> yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot Miniſters refuſing onely to Conforme; be ſo accoumpted: Becauſe, their deprivation or ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion notwithſtanding, they doe not ſeperat themſelues from the church, neither doe they (indeed) forſake the Miniſtery of the goſpell, which they deſire (before all worldly benefites whatſoever) to execure with a good conſcience, but are thruſt from it; and therefore, if men driven by exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication out of the Church be not ſchiſmatiques, much leſſe Miniſters driven by deprivation or ſuſpenſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15950:6"/> only from the execution of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery.</p>
                     <p>This word <hi>Schiſme</hi> is ſometimes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en for any diſſention in the church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>herby the peace, but not the <hi>vnity,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hereof is broken. <hi>1.</hi> Cor: <hi>11.18.</hi> In which ſenſe they are to be called <hi>ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matickes,</hi> who are ſpecially to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for ſuch diſſention. But if all the Prelates cannot giue one Argument ſoundly concluded from the word, to proue, that the Ceremonies in que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be preſcribed by authority, and yeilded unto by the Miniſtery, without ſinne, then are they Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, according to the judgment of the Apoſtle. Who beſeecheth the brethren, <hi>to marke them diligently, who cauſe diviſion &amp; offences, beſides the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which they haue learned, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd them. For they that are ſuch, ſerue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt but their owne bellies, and with faire ſpeach and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, deceiue the heartes of the ſimple.</hi>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15950:7"/> Rom. 16.17.18. By which anſwer Proteſtants doe ſufficiently juſtifie their ſeperation from Papiſtes. Much more may Miniſters juſtifie their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to Conforme yet without ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. But when any ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be given (which hath not yet been heard of) then are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters refuſing Conformity to be deemed <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi> In meane while this Poſition is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken for <hi>Petitio principii.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15950:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A <hi>PROPOSITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>CONCERNING KNEELING <hi>in the very act of receiuing</hi> Howſoever. Publiſhed to ſatisfie profeſſours, yet humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, Submitted to the iudgment of <hi>Prophets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10.11.12.</bibl>
                     <p>Why doeſt thou condemne thy brother, for it is written I liue (ſaith the Lord) and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Knee ſhall bow vnto me. So then, every one of vs ſhall giue accountes of himſelfe vnto God.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14 22.</bibl>
                     <p>Flee from Idolatry, Yee cannot be partakers of the Lords table, &amp; of the table of Deuils.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>PRINTED. 1605.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15950:8"/>
                  <head>To my Chriſtian frend, N. grace &amp; peace.</head>
                  <p>Howſoeuer it greiueth mee to heare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> much more to ſe the troubles wherewith Sathan (knowinge his time to be ſhort) doth trouble the Church of God in all places about vnprofitable and Popiſh Cerimonies, yet (to tell you the whole troth) my greife is the leſſe when I conſider that both they them ſelues, who be moſt troubleſome, and do moſt vrge thoſe Reliques of Rome be ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17, 18 Phil 3.2.19 Gal. 6.12.</note> or Dumme Dogges or, non Reſident, ſeruing their bellies, and minding Earthly thinges, euen like their Predeceſſors, who vr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged the Cerimonies of Mozes in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Churches, and their proceedinges (like them ſelues) be ſo exorbitant that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but proue odious to all men. VVhat a- matter is this, that after the Sacramentall Bread is miniſtred, the Cup ſhould be denied becauſe of not kneeling? If any of theis ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Miniſters had played ſuch apart, thoughe it were with one, <hi>openly knowne to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in ſinne notorious without repentance, whom by the</hi> 26. <hi>canon no Miniſter ſhall in any wiſe admit to the receiuing of the holy Communion,</hi> how would that Preciſian be trounced But in this Puritan Gouernement of the Church
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15950:8"/> there is no fault but <hi>non conformitie</hi> to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious vanities, A Bird of theit fether may Preach ſcores of Popiſh Doctrines, be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in life, and at his laſt caſt at dice when he hath loſt all, ſay, <hi>In the Spite of God let him do now what he can,</hi> and yet hould his owne well inough, An other mans owne and ill inough I mighte well ſay if the law might haue due courſe well, God amend all, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the remnant of this Rage. In meane while I reioice to heare that it is giuen to any of Gods people not only to beleiue in Chriſt but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake, hauing the ſame fight which they ſee or heare to be in their Miniſters,<note place="margin">Phil, 1, 27:</note> as it becommeth the Ghoſpel of Chriſt, the ſincerity wherof belongeth as well to the people as to the Miniſters of Chriſt. for howſoeuer all are not to weare the where of Babilons Smocke, yet all are to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence of bowing the knee to Baal. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme your zeale againſt the ſuperſtition of <hi>Kneeling</hi> I haue longe ſought (being often ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited ſo to do by you) and at length found a ſhort but (in my poore iudgement at leaſt to mee) a ſufficient diſcourſe which I haue printed, that I may comfort not onely you but many other alſo who are in doubt, with that comfort wherewith I my ſelfe am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted of God. I ſay Comforted. For when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15950:9"/> the iudgment is ſatisfied the heart is comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This onely I requyre of you that there be no inquiring after or geſſing at the author or publiſher. If that hurtfull curioſity were mortified learned men now fearinge that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor would be boulder to wright and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh their Godly iudgments, touching points in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſy among other I heare of a more larg &amp; learned treatiſe of this point which no doubt the authour will publiſh in time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for him if curſous heads itching eares, and wanton tongues do not hinder. In meane while let vs make as good vſe of this, as wee can. And the Lord giue vs vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all thinges</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewell</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15950:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>KNEELING IN THE VERY</hi> acte of taking, eating and drinking the <hi>Sacramentall bread and wine, in the holy</hi> Communion cannot be without ſinne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> IT is to be vnder ſtood, that, howſoeuer Kneeling may (in it ſelfe conſidered) be eſteemed a naturall geſture of the body, as <hi>ſtanding, ſitting,</hi> etc. yet in this caſe, it is by Inſtitution of man. For neiher nature nor cuſtome, doth teach vs ordinarily to knele when we eate &amp; drinke neither doth the word require <hi>Kneeling</hi> in this caſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If it be by Inſtitution, it muſt be either in reſpect of a more reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t receiuing, or Not. But if the moſt ſoleme ſigne of reuerence (vſed in theis partes of the world) be with out all reſpecte of reuerence, and that by Inſtitution of authority, in ſo high a part of Gods ſeruice may not ſuche Kneeling be iudged, if not a groſſe mocking of Chriſt, as was the ſouldiours their bowing of knes before him,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h 27.29 Mal. 1.6 7.</note> yet a taking of the name of god in vaine. Seing all ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of honour, in Gods ſeruice, ought to be to the honour
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15950:10"/> of his name,<note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 4.2 2 King 5.18.</note> and an othe not religiouſly intended (as in the nature therof it ought to be) to the honour of God, is the taking of Gods name in vaine. Did <hi>Naaman</hi> newly brought to the knowledge of God, attribut ſo much to bowing in the houſe of <hi>Rimmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> when his maſter leaned on him, ſo that it was not his volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary act? And ſhalwe, who haue had the <hi>Goſpel</hi> long, kneeling by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and determination, in a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parte of Gods ſeruice, make no accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt whether wee honour <hi>god,</hi> or no, by ſuch kneeling?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If <hi>kneeling</hi> be Inſtituted for a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent receuing, then it muſt be either in regard of God, or of bread and wine If in regard of <hi>god</hi> then muſt wee be well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that ſuch kneeling is an acceptable ſeruice vnto his Maieſtie.<note place="margin">Rom 12.1 &amp; 1, 23. Iſa 29 13. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> And that this may be, we muſt conſider, whether ſuch kneeling be a wilworſhipp or a ſeruice rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and according to Gods will. Leaſt otherwiſe we finde our ſelues ſo far from honoring God, as that we provoke him. As
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15950:10"/> did <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Levit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.1.2 3</note> who offered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſe, but not with the very fire which God appoynted,<note place="margin">1 Chro 13.10 &amp; 15.12.13.</note> and were therfore devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed with fire. And as did King David, &amp; the preiſts, who caried the Arke otherwiſe than it ought to haue been, and therefore Yzza died for it, with a ſodai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e death. For God wilbe ſanctified (if not <hi>By</hi> yet) <hi>In</hi> all them that come neere him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But kneeling is contrary to the example of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Luke 22.14. 1 Cor: 11.1.</note> who miniſtred &amp; receiued ſitting, or in ſuch a geſture, as in thoſe countryes was moſt vſed at eating. From which example to differ, without warrant from Gods word cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault. Seeing examples of holy men, much more of Chriſt, are to be followed, except there be ſome reaſonable cauſe to the contrary. And the Apoſtle to reforme an abuſe which crept (even in their times) into loue feaſtes, which were immediatly before, or after the Lords ſupper, did ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them thence, &amp; reduced the manner of adminiſtring the Lords ſupper to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15950:11"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15950:11"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15950:12"/> firſt inſtitution, ſaying:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.22 23.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall I prayſe you in this? I prayſe you not. For I haue receiued of the Lord that which I haue alſo delivered vnto you etc.</hi> Wherby it is apparant, that that forme of adminiſtration, which differeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt inſtitution, is worthy no prayſe and therfore no acceptable ſervice to God. For if the Apoſtle would not tolerate an indifferent thing (as was a loue feaſt till then) to continue ſo nere the L. ſupper, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was abuſ d, how would they allow the chaunge of ſitting into kneeling, eſpecially in theſe two conſiderations?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Firſt, becauſe the abuſe of loue feaſts (viz. <hi>ſuperfluity</hi>) was never ſo great, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dalous, in the Apoſtles time, as the abuſe of <hi>kneeling</hi> (viz. <hi>Idolatry</hi>) was and is in the ſinagogue of Rome: And beſides, Loue feaſtes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re either before, or after the L. ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ras kneeling is in the principal part of the holy Communion. Therfore if the Apoſtl baniſhed Loue feaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s from the I ſupper, becauſe of the abuſe, &amp; brought the Church to the ſimplicitie of the firſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Is it not a tempting ſinne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15950:12"/> the Idolatrous kneeling of Papiſtes, and reiect the exemplary ſitting of our M. Chriſt? And the rather, becauſe it is in that ſacrament, &amp; in that part of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which eſpecially ſetteth forth our communion with Chriſt, &amp; his Church, and is therfore called <hi>The communion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor: 10.16 17.</note> In due conſideration wherof, how can wee imagine, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath any honor by our kneeling? Seeing it ſwarneth, not only from his example, but alſo from the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of all reformed Churches, except in <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Concertatio Eccleſiae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n argu.</note> which the Papiſtes them ſelues call <hi>Puritan-papiſticall,</hi> for retainyng this, and other popiſh corruptions, and, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it may be an argument (eſpecially to a papiſt not vnderſtanding our tongue, that we haue communion with <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp; &amp; his ſinagogue, at leaſt in the Idolatry of bread worſhip. Which our failing, or care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes to avow our communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt and his church, and not abhorring all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Antichriſt &amp; his ſinagogue cannot be without grevous ſinne. Or els
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15950:13"/> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> ſinned,<note place="margin">Gal 2.11, 12 1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t. 12, 30, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> when he rebuked <hi>Peter</hi> for not holding communion with the <hi>Gentils</hi> converted, and wrote without good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, where he ſaith: <hi>If any luſt to be contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, we haue no ſuch cuſtome, neither the Churches of God.</hi> &amp; in another place: <hi>VVhat communion hath Chriſt with Beliall? Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> out, and touch no vncleane thing.</hi> Doth not God ſtreightly forbid vs to ſerue him, as Idolators doe their gods. Theſe things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, Can kneeling wherwith Papiſtes doe honor their breade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, be honorable to Chriſt, in his holy ſacrament?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Secondly, whereas the end of a ſacrament is to informe the outward man, by ſenſible d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>monſtrations, it pleaſed our M. Chriſt to vſe ſuch a geſture, as, agreably with bread and wine, ſetteth out our communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſpirituall familiaritie with him, and reioycyng in him. And therfore as he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. 3.20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ath, 8.11,</note> 
                     <hi>If any heare my voyce, and open the dore, I will come in to him, and ſup with him and he with me,</hi> ſo he ſaith, <hi>Many ſhall come from the eaſt and weſt, and ſhall ſit with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham etc.</hi> By which places it appeareth that as by <hi>ſupper,</hi> ſo by <hi>ſitting, familiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing,</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15950:13"/> or <hi>rreioycing familiarity</hi> is expreſſed. In which reſpects the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s called the <hi>Lords ſupper</hi> &amp; not A <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice,</hi> &amp; we are ſaid to be <hi>pertakers of the</hi> L. <hi>table,</hi> &amp; not of an <hi>alter.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.20 &amp; 10:21</note> And therfore not kneeling, and ſitting is for receiving. Wee read not of any geſture of bodie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, or obſerved in Circumciſion, and Baptiſme as in the Paſſover &amp; L. ſupper Becauſe there needeth no materiall regard to be had of any certaine geſture in the 2.<note place="margin">Exod 12.11 Numb. 9, 3.11.12. Math 5 17. &amp; 26.20.</note> former ſacraments, ſo the foreskynne were cut of, and water be vſed: But in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, a geſture, anſwereable to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is requiſit. And therfore God preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to his people: when they were to flie out of Egeipt, the geſture of loynes gyrded, &amp; ſtaues in their hands, becauſe the eating then of the paſſover was in haſt. But that geſture being but for that time, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare by the omisſion therof, when the ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſervation of the paſſover was eſtabliſhed, our Maſter Chriſt, who came not to break but fulfill the law, and knew what was ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15950:14"/> to be done, did not eate the paſſover ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, a geſture more anſwerable to eating in peace, than the former vſed in Egeipt. Wherby kneeling is convinced, as being a-geſture altogether vnanſwerable to eating And the rather, becauſe it darkeneth the counſell of God, and beyng a ſigne of the greateſt Submisſion obſcureth that Reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing familiaritie,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.2. 1 Cor. 11.25 26.</note> which the L. ſupper ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, and ſealeth. Doe we not condemne the papiſts for miniſtring the communion in one kinde, becauſe ſuch an admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration is againſt Chriſt his example, and doeth not liuely demonſtrate the Lords death? Here a caveat is to be given, that none take occaſion by this diſcourſe, to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the childiſh paedagogy of ſignifiynge ceremonies deviſed by man, Seeing ſitting was vſed by Chriſt, and the ſignification thereof is found in ſcripture. And therfore that childiſh paedagogy is not iuſtified by that worthy ſervant of Chriſt, M. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> his iudgment, viz. That ſitting doth ſignifie our reſt in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15950:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That kneeling may be more ſoundly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced as a wilworſhip, obiections are to be anſwered. Therfore where it is ſuppoſed that Chriſt and his Apoſtles miniſtred &amp; receiued ſitting but by occaſion, and not of purpoſe: becauſe they were ſitting before in eating the paſſeover wheras if Chriſt had ſitten down of purpoſ to adminiſter the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, then all that is ſaid is graunted to be ſome purpoſe. The anſwer is ſhort, yet full: Chriſt did ſit of purpoſe, when he mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtred his laſt ſupper. For after the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over he roſe, waſhed his diſciples feet, and ſat downe againe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> If it be demaunded, why the Church is not bound to the time of evening, as well as to the geſture of ſitting, ſith Chriſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the one, as well as the other? It may be anſwered: Time being a common cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunce to every action (for nothing can be done,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Gen. 2, 2 3.</note> but in ſome time) the perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar time is not to be obſerued, except Chriſt had ſanctified it to the communion, as God ſainctified the <hi>7.</hi> day, on which he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15950:15"/> reſted,<note place="margin">Math 26.31:<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5 Lek 22.53</note> or (at leaſt) choſen it of purpoſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he did <hi>ſitting.</hi> But wheras it was vpon ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall, and neceſſary occaſion, for the paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver muſt eaten before the L. ſupper could be inſtituted inſteed therof, and preſently after ſupper the hower came, when Chriſt was to be betrayed, therefore if the Iewes tranſgreſſed not the inſtitution of the paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, by chaunging a geſture, at the firſt preſcribed by God according to that their preſent occaſion, in another ſitter for a ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of reſt, much leſſe doe chriſtians tranſgreſe the inſtitution of the L. ſupper, by chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the time taken by Chriſt vpon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not preſcribed, into ſome other fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (in diſcretion) for the ordinarie cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the L. ſupper. As probably the Primitiue Churches did. For every firſt day of the weeke (viz. the L. day) the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren came togither to breake bread,<note place="margin">Act 2:42. &amp; 20.7: 1 Cor: 16, 2. Revel: 1.10:</note> 
                     <hi>id eſt, to miniſter the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> So that either th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y never met vpon the L. day, but in the evenning, or elſe they celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the communion at ſome other times,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15950:15"/> but for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y alteration of the geſtures of ſitting, eſpecially into kneeling there is not the leaſt probabilitie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> It is further obiected. That we may kneele in regard of prayers to be vſed, by preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of authority, at the deliueryng of the bread and wine. <hi>viz. The bodie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt which was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thee, preſeru thy bodie and ſoule into eternall life, and take and eate this. etc.</hi> Heere vnto theſe anſwers may be returned. Seing we reiect Chriſt his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ſitting for kneeling, we muſt not ſtand vpon what we may doe, but humbly conſider what we <hi>muſt doe.</hi> For if there be not a neceſſary, and a iuſtifiable cauſe both of thoſe prayers, and of Kneeling in regard of them, doe we not preſume vpon Chriſt his patience, in reiecting his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Now, what necesſitie is there of thoſe prayers, at that very time? Seeing prayers goe before, and follow after. Againe, muſt we needs kneele at every bitte of a prayer? Is their more necesſity to obey a needleſſe direction to kneele at thoſe prayers, than to follow the example of Chriſt, In ſitting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15950:16"/> when we take eate and drinke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyred in the ſame ſentences? And w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> muſt the people kneele, when they hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe prayers, rather than the miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> who pronounceth them? But it is a queſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, Whither thoſe prayers be iuſtifiable o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no. For beſides that, by reaſon of them, <hi>Kneeling,</hi> deviſed and abuſed by Anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chriſt, doth croſſe the practiſe of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and his Apoſtles, and they may ſeeme a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vayne repitition: Even the adding of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to the words of inſtitution is contrary t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the minde of Chriſt. For he did firſt bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or pray, and after gaue the Elements, in a ſacramentall forme of words,<note place="margin">Math. 6 7 &amp; 26 26. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Mark 14.21 Luk: 22.19, etc:</note> without any addition, ſaying, <hi>take, eate,</hi> etc. Which order of adminiſtration, and forme of words, <hi>Mathew, Marke, Luke,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> doe ſo conſtantly, preciſly, and ſincerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, that any may perceiue the meaning of the ſpirit to be. That the ſacramentall forme of words ought preciſely to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, without any addition. And the rather becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> beginneth his relation thus,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15950:16"/> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aue receiued of the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11, 23 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4,</note> 
                     <hi>that which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aue alſo deliuered,</hi> etc. So that it may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>me to be againſt religion and reaſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at to a ſacramentall forme of ſpeach, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herin the miniſter ſhould only ſupply the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rſon of Chriſt, there ſhould be added a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rayer, as in the name of the Church. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fuſion is fitter for Babilon, than for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on. Laſtly, Why is not a ſhort prayer, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r other going before, aſwell ioyned to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cramentall forme of Baptiſme: viz. N. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aptiſe thee In the name of the Father, etc.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> then this addition of prayer to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall forme of words, be not of faith,<note place="margin">Rom 14.5, 23</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow can we, with faith and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ce, confirme, or allow the ſame with our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neeling?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Laſtly for iuſtifiyng of <hi>Kneeling,</hi> it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffirmed. That it is indifferent whither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſitt, ſtand, or kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: Seeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> did ſit, when he did eate the paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r. Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as <hi>God</hi> commaunded the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dren of <hi>Iſrael <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Egipt</hi> to eate the <hi>paſſover</hi> ſtanding, and ſome reformed churches receiue ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15950:17"/> for all that Chriſt did ſit at his laſt ſupper: Therfore the King may appoynt <hi>Kneeling,</hi> as the moſt reverend geſture, and beſt beſeeming ſo holy an action. For anſwer whervnto, howſoever that which is alreadie ſaid, may ſuffice, Yet it may be further co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſidered, That though it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, that it is indifferent to ſit, or to ſtand, yet it doth not follow, that <hi>Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> is indifferent, For <hi>ſitting</hi> is the exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, and <hi>ſtanding</hi> is a geſture ſometimes vſed in ordinary eating, and (in the obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) it is ſaid to be preſcribed at a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall feaſt. Againe, It doth not follow, That becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> vſed a geſture fitter for eating in his time, inſteed of a geſture preſcribed vpon occaſion, it is therfore law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full to vſe a geſture nothing anſwerable to eating, and that taken out of the <hi>Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (as though the word of God came out of it,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.36</note> or to it onely) inſtead of a geſture moſt anſwerable to eating, &amp; of purpoſe vſed by Chriſt at the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacrament. So that, notwithſtanding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15950:17"/> all that is ſaid for Kneling, His Maieſtie (vpon whome the burthern as of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſo of other ceremonies, is layde) may remember,<note place="margin">2 Chro<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 29 25,</note> That <hi>Hezekiah</hi> appoynted <hi>Levites</hi> in the houſe of the Lord with Ci<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls, etc. according to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> the Kings Seer, and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement was by the hand of the Lord, and by the hand of his prophets. And withall conſider, that if <hi>Kneeling</hi> were the moſt revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t geſture, &amp; beſt be ſeming the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, our L. &amp; Maſter would not haue ſitten downe of purpoſe, at his laſt ſupper. And that <hi>Ahaz</hi> was deceiued In deeming the Alter at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 K ng 16 10, 12:14 15</note> more honorable for Gods ſervice, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the alter of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Having ſaid that which may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to a man reaſonable, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, againſt the iuſtitution of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for ſuppoſed reverence in regard of God, it remaineth that ſomewhat be ſaid againſt the inſtitution of <hi>Kneeling,</hi> for reverence in regard of bread and wine.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15950:18"/> Which need not be much, For no ſound proteſtant, of any knowledge, will affirme it, but rather preſently conſider, That if kneeling be inſtituted for reverence in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of bread and wine, It muſt be either becauſe they repreſent the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt, though remaining bread and wine touching there ſubſtaunce: And then for like reaſon, we may worſhip the cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe, and image of God, as the papiſts doe: Or, becauſe Chriſt is really, bodily, &amp; local<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, though inviſibly, preſent in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either by <hi>Tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation,</hi> according to the heriſy of the papiſts, or by <hi>conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> according to the heriſy of the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rans.</hi> Theſe things cannot but be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, And then it muſt needs follow, that if we abiure theſe heriſyes of Papiſts, &amp; <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> we muſt alſo abhorre idolatrous, &amp; ſuperſtitious kneeling, their <hi>daughter</hi> and <hi>Nurſe,</hi> which was never hearde of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was hatched in the ſinagogue of Antichriſt.<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> So that imme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatly after Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> decreed <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15950:18"/> Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> decreed kneeling.<note place="margin">Aunſ to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Iuels ch fol. 111</note> Therfore if <hi>Harding</hi> doth grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it is not well to kneele: but in regard of a reall, &amp; bodily preſence, a ſound pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſhould infer, But I deteſt your reall preſence, therfore I abhorre your Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous kneeling.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> We are to abhorre kneeling, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we abhorre the heriſyes of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping images, Tranſubſtantiation, &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, but alſo, Becauſe it is the ſhew of the greateſt evils that ever were, viz <hi>Idolatry</hi> in worſhipping a God made of a peice of bread,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and of communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Antichriſt, rather than, with Chriſt, and therfore the greateſt ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dall that ever was or can be, both in regard of thoſe evils it doth occaſionally teach, or confirme, As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in regard of multituds (indeed the moſt part of people) either not ſuffice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the right vnderſtanding, &amp; vſe of the ſacrament, and therfore caried with a blinde devotion learned by tradition, or corrupted (more or leſſe) with the leaven
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15950:19"/> of poperie. Who all in regard of their weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, are indangered by this geſture, either groſly to commit the Idolatry of papiſts, or to haue a ſuperstitious estimation of the cutward elements. And the rather, becauſe by the 21 Canon it is provided: <hi>That no b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ead, and wine newly brought, ſhalbe vſed, but firſt the words of inſtitution ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, when the ſaid bread &amp; wine be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vpon the Communion table.</hi> As if the words were incantations, &amp; the table like the aulter which ſanctifieth the ſacrifice. May not this prouiſo ſeeme (at leaſt to the ſimple) to make way at leaſt to the Popiſh conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ration? How grevous a ſinne it is to ſcandalize the make,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h, 18.6.</note> may appeare by the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> viz. <hi>whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little ones, it were better for him, that a milſtone were hanged about his ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e, and that he were drowned in the depth of the Sea.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o 8.13.</note> And of Paul: <hi>If meate offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my brother. I will ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e no fleſh, while the world ſtandeth, that I may not offend my brother.</hi> What an offence or ſcandall is, the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhew th in the ſame chapter, <hi>viz. An occaſion of fallyng to the weake.</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15950:19"/> The perticular offence he ſpeaketh of is this: Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the goſpell was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a convenient time, and that by the Apoſtles, yet many wanted knowledge, &amp;,<note place="margin">verſ 7:10.</note> even vnto that time, did eate as a thing ſacrificed to an Idoll. Of whome if any ſhould ſee a man indued with knowledge ſit at table in the Idols temple, his weake conſcience might occaſionally be imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to eate thoſe things which are ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to Idols. If Paul would never eate fleſh rather than he would offend in this caſe, becauſe in ſo doeing he ſhould ſinne agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt Chriſt, how dare a chriſtian,<note place="margin">ver. 12</note> hauing know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, kneele in the preſence of any, who, for want of knowledge, receiue ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. Of which ſort, ſeing there be ſo many even vntill this hower, and ever likly to be, that we know not when, and where to communicate without ſome ſuch, either old, or young: it followeth, that as ſitting at table in the Idols temple, could not be with out ſinne, in the Apoſtles time, ſo kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling cannot be without ſin in theſe dayes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15950:20"/> when the number of faithfull teachers is much decreaſed, but of papiſts much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, &amp; by our kneeling much confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their bread worſhipe.<note place="margin">Sum of the confe. pa. 74</note> Therfore If his Maieſties iudgment be ſound, that the ſurplice is not to be worne, if <hi>Heatheniſh men were commorant among vs, who, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, might take occaſion to be ſtrengthened in their paganiſme?</hi> ſhall we by our corrupt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of <hi>kneeling,</hi> strengthen the papiſts, who ſwarme among us, in their Idolatry? If the <hi>State</hi> doth well, in ordeining the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to be adminiſtred in vſual bread to take away ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Rub. after the com, ſect 5.</note> wheras Chriſt did by occaſion, miniſter in vnleave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed bread, ſhall not we doe ill, In teaching, or confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſuperſtition by kneeling, whereas Chriſt did of purpoſe miniſter ſitting?<note place="margin">Hom. agaiſt peril of Idol part 3 a</note> Set<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting vp of images in churches onely to be lay mens bookes, is, by authoritie condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">Levit: 19.14</note> becauſe they are as <hi>ſtumbling blockes in way of the blinde So that they haue been, are ſtill, and will be hereafter worſhipped by ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſons.</hi> Is not kneeling as ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous? How can it then be iuſtified?</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15950:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> But it is ſaid, that the Kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t taketh away ſcandall, in things indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And it may be averred that this is a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the queſtion, except it be proued by the word, that kneeling may be without ſinne, and that notwithſtanding it be an inſtitution of man, contrary to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, a ſigne of communion rather with Antichriſt and his ſinagogue of Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, than with Chriſt and his Church, it haue no proportion with ſacramentall eating, and haue beene, is, and will be bread wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipe. But ſuppoſe that in it ſelfe it wereas indifferent as was eating of fleſh ſacrificed to an Idol, not in the Idols temple,<note place="margin">1 Cor: 10.17 28.</note> but at a priuate table where no weake ones were, in the Apoſtles time: yet how doth the Kings commaundement take away ſcandall from kneeling in publicke places? Doth it make all ſo ſure, that none can be ſcandalized? Or, if that cannot be, doth it take away guiltines from the ſcandalizer, as if all the blame of ſcandalizing, were in the Kings commaundement? Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rly it muſt be in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15950:21"/> former, or els the latter cannot be, For by ſcandalizing a weake brother periſheth.<note place="margin">Cor 8.11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mb: 35</note> Of whoſe bloud, the ſcandalizer is guiltie, as <hi>Ioab</hi> was of <hi>Vriahs</hi> bloud,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am, 11:15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 17,</note> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Kings commaundement. Here his Maieſtie knowne to be of a gentle diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, &amp; to haue learned, yea profeſſed bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter thinges in <hi>Scotland,</hi> is moſt humblie prayed, to take this word (King) as ſpoken in imitation, and vnderſtood of <hi>Cantor:</hi> who knowne to be of a violent diſpoſition, did cary matters in the Convocation, and publiſhed Canons not orderly, &amp; fully con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded, as ſome of his ſuffragane prelates report, But it is imposſible, that the Kings commaundement ſhould make all ſo ſure, that none can be ſcandalized, the generall ignorance of the people, the diſpoſition of the ignorant vnto ſuperſtition, the old lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of popery not purged, &amp; the multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of papiſts, all well conſidered. Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, It is likely, that by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſcandall will be the greater. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially in regard of the 27 Canon, where
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15950:21"/> miniſters are commaunded, vnder paine of <hi>ſuſpenſion, Not wittingly to adminiſter the ſacrament to any, but ſuch as kneele.</hi> May not ſimple, &amp; ſuperſtitious perſons take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thus to argue? Why ſhould kneeling be thus vrged by authoritie, if the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſignes of the bodie, and bloud of Chriſt, be no more to be reverenced, than water applyed in baptizing children? See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is alſo a ſanctified ſigne of Chriſt his bloud, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſheth away our ſinnes, and iniquities.</p>
                  <p>To conclud, If <hi>kneeling</hi> in the very acte of <hi>taking, eating</hi> &amp; <hi>drinking</hi> the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall bread &amp; wine, in the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion, be (1) an inſtitution of man. (2) If it be the taking of Gods name in vaine, when it is without all reſpecte of reverence (3) If God be not honored thereby, except it be according to his will. (4) If it ſwarue from the example of Chriſt his ſitting, &amp; therfore deſerueth no prayſe. (5) If it be a provoking ſinne to reiect the exemplary ſitting of chriſt, wherby we ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w our ſelues
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15950:22"/> to be in communion with Chriſt, &amp; the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed churches, and to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>taine kneeling, which for bread worſhip, ought to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp; wherby we ſeeme to be in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Antichriſt, &amp; his ſinagogue. 6) If it obſcureth that reioycing familiaritie in &amp; with Chriſt which the L. ſupper ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth (7) if the argument from Chriſt his example be made the ſtronger, in that he ſat of purpoſe. 8) If the lawfulnes of cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing a fitter time than the euening cannot iuſtify our reiecting Chriſt his exemplary ſitting (9) if the bittes of prayer ioyned with the words of inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do make knel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the more ſinfull (10) If kneeling be not as indifferent, as ſtanding, nor beſt beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the holy communion, and the King muſt appoynt nothing but by the hand of the Lord. (11) If we ought to abhor knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as we abhorre the worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> (12) If to ſcandalize be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly to ſinne, and kneeling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e a ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w of the greateſt evils, and withall the great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15950:22"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>candall. And (13) If it be a begging of be queſtion to affirme, kneeling to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, &amp; the Kings commaundement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſo called) doth rather increaſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leſſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>candall by kneeling, It may be averred, that kneeling in the very acte of Taking, eating, and drinking the ſacramentall bread &amp; wine, in the holy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot be without ſinne.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <head>The Printer to the reader.</head>
                  <p>The copy ſent me wanted direction for the quotations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; I wanted an Engliſh corrector therfore haue I failed more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen I would: eſpecially in placing them. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut pardon I pray, and take knowledge of theſe principals:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata,</head>
                  <p>Pag 2 put downe Rom, 16, 17, 18, phil, 3, 2. 19, gal, 6, 12 lines, 2 pag, 5, pu, d, mal. 1, 6, 7. l 2 pa 6, 2 king 5, 18 l 3, pa 7, 1 cor. 11, 1, l 5, pa 10, 1 cor, 11, 16 l 3 &amp; 2 cor 6, 15, 17 l 4, &amp; deut 12, 30, 31 l 5, math 8, 11 l 2, pa, 11 ſet vp 1 cor 11, 20 &amp; 10, 21 l 2 &amp; p, d, exo, 12 11 16, num, 3, 11, 12 math, 5, 17 &amp; 26, 20 l 12. pa 12, l 1. put out not. &amp; ſet vp Iob 38. 2 l 1, p, d, 1 cor, 11, 25, 26, l 6, pa 13 ſ, v: Iohn 13, 4, 12 l 10. p, d gen, 2, 2, 3, l 3. pa: 14 pu, d: Math 26: 31: 45: Luke 22:53: lin 4 read muſt be eaten lin 11. read into another. pa. 16. li: 2 read ſentences preſcribed &amp; ſ: v: math 6. 7 l 5</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
